Ralph Chesse papers, 1935-1975
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections Research Center
Ralph Chesse papers
1935-1975
C0224
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections Research Center
1.25 linear feet (1.5 boxes, 1 flat box)
The Chesse papers contain materials such as photographs, watercolor set and costume design sketches, playscripts, and programs relating to Federal Theatre Project marionette productions in San Francisco and Los Angeles. Some of these plays are Child of God, Crock of Gold, The Emperor Jones, Hansel and Gretel, Marionette Varieties, Rip Van Winkle, The Tempest, and Twelfth Night. The papers also include magazine articles from the 1970s that highlight Chesse's mural painting at the Coit Tower in San Francisco.
Chesse, Ralph
Biographical Information
Ralph Chesse was born in New Orleans, Louisiana on January 6, 1900. He attended schools in New Orleans and Chicago including the Chicago Art Institute, but was primarily a self-taught painter. In 1924 he traveled to San Francisco where he met the puppeteer Blanding Sloan. It was after this meeting that Chesse began working as a puppeteer. In 1929 he opened his first puppet theatre, The Marionette Guild on Merchant Street. In 1934 Chesse was selected, with a mural design titled "Playground," as one of 26 artists by the Works Progress Administration to paint a wall fresco inside of Coit Tower. During this same year The Marionette Guild had to close due to lack of funds.
Chesse joined the Federal Theatre project in 1936 as Director of the Puppetry Unit. There he oversaw a crew of 17 people. Their first production was The Crock of Gold in 1936. Other early productions included The Mikado, Alice in Wonderland, A Marionette Variety Show, and Emperor Jones.
The Federal Theatre Project was a division of the Works Progress Administration (WPA), which provided employment for large numbers of artists, writers, and performers during the Great Depression (1929-1939). The Federal Theatre began in 1935 and, until its end in 1939, flourished as the first and only federally sponsored and subsidized theater program in the United States. Directed by Hallie Flanagan (1880-1969), it was a way for theatrical professionals to gain employment during the Depression. Jobs were provided for many people, including actors, playwrights, scene designers, scene builders, seamstresses, lighting experts, ushers, box-office men, and stagehands.
In 1937 Chesse moved to Los Angeles to take over as State Director for California. This was a larger unit employing 50 people. He remained in Los Angeles until 1939 though was still in communication with activities in San Francisco. In Los Angeles productions included Rip Van Winkle, Snow White and the Seven Dwarves, and a Variety Show. On June 30th 1939 the puppetry unit received notice that the Federal Theatre Project had been terminated. Also in 1939 Chesse brought marionettes to the World's Fair held in San Francisco.
After work finished with the FTP Chesse moved his family back to San Francisco and had a long and successful career that included various jobs. At different points in his life Chesse made a living by teaching puppetry for adult education classes at San Francisco State College, producing a children's television program called The Wonderful World of Brother Buzz, making puppets for TV, theatre, and opera, and acting in plays and films. In 1984 he moved to Ashland, Oregon where he was an avid painter up until his death in 1991. He died of heart failure.
Arrangement
Organized alphabetically by title. Oversize materials are separated physically but integrated intellectually in this finding aid.
Scope and Content
The Chesse papers contain materials such as photographs, watercolor set and costume design sketches, playscripts, and programs relating to Federal Theatre Project marionette productions in San Francisco and Los Angeles. Some of these plays are Child of God, Crock of Gold, The Emperor Jones, Hansel and Gretel, Marionette Varieties, Rip Van Winkle, The Tempest, and Twelfth Night. The papers also include magazine articles from the 1970s that highlight Chesse's mural painting at the Coit Tower in San Francisco.
Acquisition Information
Donated to Special Collections Research Center by Ralph Chesse on July 8, 1977; July 24, 1980; May 18, 1981.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Related Material
The Works Progress Administration oral histories collection, the Federal Theatre Project collection, the Federal Theatre Project photograph collection, as well as numerous other personal papers.
Alternative Form Available
Digitized photographs from this collection can be found in the.
Index Terms
Persons:
Chesse, Ralph.
Corporate Names:
Federal Theatre Project (Los Angeles, Calif.); Federal Theatre Project (San Francisco, Calif.); Federal Theatre Project (U.S.)
Subjects:
New Deal, 1933-1939.; Puppet theater.; Theater--United States.
Contents List
- Ralph Chesse papers, 1935-1975
  - Child of God costume designs, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    8 items
  - Child of God playscript, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Child of God set designs, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    4 items
  - City of San Francisco magazine, February 4, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Includes article with section about Chesse "The WPA and the great Coit Tower controversy: The artists look back".
  - Crock of Gold photographs, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    8 photographs
    - Crock of Gold, March 1936
    - Crock of Gold, March 1936
  - Crock of Gold playscript, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    photocopy
  - Crock of Gold set design, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    5 items
  - The Cue volume I number II, August 1936 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Includes interview with Ralph Chesse.
  - The Emperor Jones playbill, circa 1937 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - The Emperor Jones photograph, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - The Emperor Jones set design, circa 1937 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    3 items
  - The Farmer's wife playbill, circa 1936-1939 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - The Federal Show Parade volume I number II, May 10, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Hamlet costume design; Hansel and Gretel set design, 1926; circa 1936-1939 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Four items, Hamlet costume design is photocopy, set designs are watercolors
  - Help Yourself playbill, April 1937 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Hula group marionettes photograph, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - It Can't Happen Here newspaper clipping, October 19, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Los Angeles marionette theatre photographs, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Four photographs - two of traveling stage with curtain drawn; two of audience.
  - Marionette band photograph, circa 1936-1939 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Marionette crew of San Francisco, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    2 photographs
  - Marionette personnel, circa 1936-1939 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Marionette stage design, circa 1936-1939 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Marionette Varieties San Francisco production, July 1936; 1938 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    27 photographs
  - The Marriage Proposal, July 1936 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - The murals in Coit Tower, December 14, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    article in San Francisco Examiner and Chronicle
  - Penguin Island costume design, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    12 items
  - A puppeteer's guide, circa 1935-1939 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - R. U. R. costume designs, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - R. U. R. script for marionettes, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - R. U. R. set designs, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Rip Van Winkle Los Angeles marionette production, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    4 photographs
  - San Francisco Sunday Examiner and Chronicle: Conversation with a puppeteer, April 28, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Schedule of productions, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Sherlock Holmes, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Photocopy of script; photographs of marionette performance.
  - Snow White script, circa 1937 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - The Tempest, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Color slides of set and costume design sketches for The Tempest.
  - The Tempest costume designs, 1935; 1937 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    17 items
  - The Tempest set designs, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - They walked with beauty: Gauguin, Cezanne, Van Gogh, August 1-September 5, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    4 radioscripts
  - Twelfth Night San Francisco marionette production, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Twelfth Night costume design, 1937 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Twelfth Night set design, circa 1937-1938 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - World's Fair, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    Two photographs of Chesse demonstrating how marionettes work to two women.
  - U-matic recording of marionette Macbeth act I, performed at California Academy of Sciences, December 30, 1979 (Box 2)
  - U-matic recording of marionette Macbeth act II, performed at California Academy of Sciences, December 30, 1979 (Box 2)